# 恨不得就是直接从鸡圈里面
If I can, I would actually just grab a chicken from the yard
# 或者是从散养的鸡里面
Or from the free-range fields.
# 抓一只鸡来煮
And cook it as fresh as possible
# 煮完之后就拌
Boil it and prepare this dish
# 一下就激发出来了 但不能多了
The flavours are coming out, but don’t over-do it
# 在我们乐山 我们从小到大
In Le Shan, we grew up with this dish
# 好多年好多年好多年的
Year by year
# 椒麻鸡
Jiao Ma Chicken (Spicy chicken with Sichuan Pepper)
# 我这个鸡 它要开水下锅
We need to cook it with boiling water
# 放点姜片 放点大葱
Ginger and spring onion
# 放一点白芷 放一点花椒
A bit of Baizhi (Angelica dahurica) and Sichuan Pepper
# 白芷是杀菌 然后增加肉香的
Baizhi helps to improve the flavour of the meat
# 花椒是去腥的
Sichuan pepper removes the gamey tastes
# 然后放一点黄酒 这个不能放太多了
A bit of the Huangjiu rice wine, not too much
# 然后这个鸡我稍微处理一下
Let me prepare this chicken
# 你可以整只的煮
You can boil the whole chicken
# 也可以从中间劈开
You can also cut it open from the middle
# 你的小鸡挺嫩啊
This chicken is quite tender
# 采用的是散养的这种小公鸡
Yes, it’s a free-ranged rooster
# 这样的肉质 它会比较结实
The meat is quite firm
# 口感才会比较好一点 这样劈开
And it will taste better. Let’s open it up like this
# 然后下鸡有一个讲究
There is a tip in boiling the chicken
# 三上三下
You first dip it in and out three times like this
# 先过一下把皮紧一下
To firm-up the skin
# 然后这样再下去
Then you put it in the water
# 一个是能够去掉它的腥味
This removes the gamey flavour
# 再一个使它皮紧实 待会煮出来好一点
Also the skin will stay firm after boiling
# 好了 现在做一个非常关键的东西
Now, we work on something very important.
# 椒麻鸡么 其实在于椒麻
The key to this dish, is the Chili and Sichuan peppers
# 藤椒
Tenjiao Sichuan pepper (Zanthoxylum armatum)
# 特别在我们乐山老家
This is popular in my hometown Le Shan
# 家家户户门口都会有一两棵树
Everyone will grow one or two trees outside their house,
# 从树上摘下来 安逸
You go and pick it when you are cooking. Very nice.
# 这个很简单
This is simple
# 花椒它表皮富含油包
The pericarp is rich in oil content
# 我们需要把油稍微烧热一点点 菜籽油
We just need to heat up a bit of rapeseed oil
# 不要烧的太过了
Don’t over-cook it
# 这个菜为什么叫椒麻鸡 就跟这个有关
This is how the dish gets its name
# 这个菜籽油有两种说法
About the rapeseed oil, there’s some debate about it
# 一个是要把它炼到冒青烟
Some say you need to heat it up until it smokes
# 然后让它过了 没有菜籽油的味道
Let the smoke run out to get rid of the excess smell
# 其实不然 一定要刚好冒烟
Actually, that’s not totally true. We only need to heat till it just starts to smoke.
# 能闻到菜籽油的香味的时候
The moment when you start to smell it
# 现在已经闻到了
Like now.
# 有味道是吧 刚好冒烟 咱就可以了
Do you smell it? And it’s just starting to smoke, that’s it.
# 这个香味刚刚好
Perfect timing.
# 如果你油温太高就炸枯了
Over-heating the oil will dry out the Sichuan pepper
# 这道菜的关键
The key to this dish
# 是对油的把控 和温度的把控
Is to get the oil and temperature correct
# 我们把这个先放一边
Let’s put it aside
# 然后来一个更关键的
Another key point
# 我们做一个红油
Is the red chili oil
# 红油这个辣椒特别有讲究
The choice of chili peppers is important
# 四川二荆条
We use the “Erjingtiao” chili pepper from Sichuan
# 既有颜色 又有香味 然后还有辣味
It’s got the color, the aroma and the hotness
# 二荆条我放点芝麻
We also need a bit of sesame
# 然后这个时候加点生油 生的菜籽油
Let’s mix it up with some raw rapeseed oil
# 叫它拌一拌 它不至于糊了
It prevents the chili pepper from burning
# 一个是不至于糊了
That’s one
# 一个是它待会有生菜籽油的香味
It also adds a layer of the raw rapeseed aroma
# 好了油温也上来了
Alright the oil is heated up
# 香葱和大葱也要放一点点
A bit of chives and spring onion
# 炸的颜色变黄
Keep frying until it turns yellow
# 这个时候我放一点香料
Now let’s put the spices in
# 八角 这几个香料是增加油的香味
Star anise, for the aroma
# 桂皮 白蔻 三奈 香叶 小茴香
Cinnamon, white cardamon, sand ginger, bay leaves and fennel seeds
# 这个为什么这个时候下呢
Why now ?
# 因为葱炸出来之后
Because you don’t want to over-cook the spices
# 这个香料它不要炸的太过
After frying the spring onions
# 桂皮 大料 香叶 小茴香 三奈 白蔻
Cinnamon, star anise, bay leaves, fennel seeds, sand ginger, and white cardamon.
# 你看香料的综合的香味出来了
You can smell the complex aroma from all of the spices
# 我现在要把它温度降一降
We need to lower the temperature a bit
# 温度太高了 辣椒面要糊了
Otherwise it will burn the chili flakes
# 先试第一遍 看它的热度怎么样
Let’s give it a test see if it’s hot enough
# 如果热度不够 然后增加它的热度
If not, then we can bring the heat up.
# 热度差点 再稍微提一点温度
It’s not hot enough.
# 其实第一次把它和匀了之后
It’s fine to mix it up first
# 把温度烧上来 呲啦一下去
And then pour some hot oil afterwards
# （篦出小料）这样出来辣椒面更漂亮一点
Use the sieve to remove the spices
# 好 这个温度绝对可以了
OK we it’s good enough now
# 放完油之后不要动它
Don’t move it, let it sit
# 动了之后的辣椒面
If you do
# 跟它最后沉淀的香味是不一样的
The flavour and aroma will be affected.
# 这个时候放一点点的米醋
Now, let’s add some rice vinegar
# 降降它的温度
To bring down the temperatures
# 放米醋的作用是 增加辣椒的香味
It also stimulates the flavour
# 同时增加它的辣度
The hotness
# 一下就激发出来了
Letting them burst out
# 但不能多了 多了就酸了
But not too much, otherwise it will get sour.
# 你看这个 是不是有白芷的香味
Look, do you smell the whit cardamon ?
# 这个我煮了有差不多七八分钟
I cooked it for about 7-8 minutes
# 但泡要泡十几分钟
And let it soak for over ten minutes
# 煮是让它熟制的过程 泡是让它浸透
So that it cooks all the way through
# 这个鸡煮熟了
Now that the chicken it cooked
# 然后我要在冰水里面拔一下
I need to dip it in ice water
# 吃起来爽
To make the skin crispy
# 口感的话还有肉香味
The texture and the flavour
# 它会更好一点
Will also improve
# 然后冰水拔完了之后 稍微拿出来晾一晾
After that, let it drain a bit
# 要不它水汽太重 改一下刀
to remove the excess water. Then let’s cut it into pieces
# 完完整整的呈现一下
Keep the parts intact
# 包括鸡爪子都很好吃的
Including the feet. They taste very good.
# 吃鸡一定要啃着鸡骨头吃 越啃越香
Chicken tastes much better with the bones.
# 而且鸡骨头还能吸味
The bones also help to improve the flavour.
# 我这切了点大葱丁
Here are some spring onion.
# 剁成蒜末之后加点水 蒜水
Garlic was finely chopped and soaked in water
# 加点姜水 它会让味道更加充分
Same with ginger.
# 加一点味精
A little bit of MSG
# 这个味精不要多了 因为鸡肉比较鲜
Not too much as the chicken already has a lot of umami flavour.
# 我要放一点酱油
A bit of soy sauce
# 黄豆酱油一个是能拔色 一个能提鲜
For the colour as well as extra umami flavour.
# 给一点点的盐
A bit of salt
# 这个东西可以上调下调的
You can adjust to your own taste of course
# 来一个最关键的东西 椒麻
Now, the key ingredient, Chili pepper and Sichuan pepper
# 刚才不是搞了这么多香料
We used so many spices
# 整得这么复杂的红油
To make such a complicated chili oil
# 香味非常的香
The aroma is amazing
# 而且是现烫的红油才是最香的
The best is to make the chili oil on spot
# 如果你提前烫放那
If you make it too early in advance
# 它就没有那个感觉了
It doesn’t taste as good.
# 现烫的花椒油 现烫的红油 特别香
Freshly made Sichuan pepper oil and chili pepper oil are the best
# 这个辣椒是用二荆条
Remember that we used the “Eerjingtiao” chili pepper
# 又有颜色 又有味道 又有香味
It has everything we need, the colour, the flavour and the aroma
# 稍微给重一点
We can use a bit more of this
# 为什么川菜吃了香
Why does Sichuan food taste so good?
# 它一般的油都比较大
They are bold with using oil
# 没有油气它就不香
You need sufficient oil to bring out the flavour
# 这个时候我还要加一点点的原汤
Now, we need a bit of the chicken stock
# 原汤来一点 不要多了
Just a little bit, not too much
# 让它能够把调料给化一下
This will help mixing the sauce
# 这样的鸡肉里面带一点汤汁
And give extra juiciness to the meat
# 还差一点白糖 增加它的鲜味
We also need a bit of sugar to intensify the taste
# 第二个是中和
It makes the spices a bit milder
# 第三个稍微有一点增香和去腥
It also improves the aroma and removes any unwanted taste
# 好了温温的
Alright, it’s still warm
# 然后这个时候我再放一点小米辣
Lastly, some fresh “Xiaomila” chili pepper
# 这个时候放花椒粉
Grounded Sichuan pepper
# 这个关键点 也是现焙的
Which we also made freshly
# 其实这就好了
That’s pretty much it!
# 好勒 然后再撒一点葱花
A bit of chopped spring onion
# 这个时候再来点花椒面
Finish with a bit more grounded Sichuan pepper
# 更有特色 味道十足
Give it more character
# 这就是 乐山的椒麻鸡
There we have it, the Spicy chicken with Sichuan pepper, from Le Shan
# 好了好了不要太多
OK that’s enough
# 好香
Tastes good!
# 因为有骨头 牙啃不动
My teeth are not good enough for the bones.
# 杨兵做这个椒麻鸡  味道十足
Chef Bing YANG did a good job in this dish.
# 真是体现了乐山的地方的文化
It represents the culture of Le Shan
# 而且乐山的味道
The taste of Le Shan
# 综合的味道非常地道
The complex flavour is as good as we would expect
# 安逸 巴适
Nice, very nice.
# 二伯牙口好 吃的香
Er Bai has a good appetite today!
# 他这个椒麻鸡 味道甭说了
This it as good as it gets. I am speechless.
# 味道杠杠的
The flavour is spot on!
# 但是它的过程非常重要
The procedures to make this dish is very important
# 每个细节组合在一块
It’s all about those little details
# 体现出了今天的最佳味道
That makes this nice taste.
# 我们爱川菜
We love Sichuan cuisine
# 我爱川菜的味道
We love its flavour
# 更爱火辣辣的性格
And the spicy characters of the people.
# 您最爱吃哪种泡菜
What’s your favourite type of pickled vegetables?
# 我最爱吃四川泡菜
I love the ones from Sichuan
# 爱吃四川泡菜
That’s my favourite
# 我特别喜欢用泡菜烧鱼吃
Especially to cook fish with it
# （鱼）切成肉丁
Cut the fish into small blocks
# 用这泡菜 我给它剁碎了
Finely chop the pickled vegetables
# 用泡菜就跟烧干烧鱼似的
Cook them like the red-braised fish.
# 烧完了 （用）泡菜红红的搁上
Finish with some red pickled vegetables
# 特别好吃 可好吃了
Amazing flavour.
# 泡菜给它剁碎了
If you chop it up
# 剁的极细
Really finely chopped
# 然后用泡菜烧丸子吃
You can also cook them with meatballs
# 他们淮阳的丸子很嫩
Like the tender meatballs from Huai Yang
# 用泡菜这个方法
Cooked in this way
# 两个一结合也好吃
It’s also great.
# 喝这个泡菜丸子汤
Meatball soup with pickled vegetables
# 开胃爽口 听着就好喝
What could possibly go wrong ?
# 一九五七年
In 1957
# 成都饮食行业协会
The Culinary association of Chengdu published,
# 为四川泡菜
Specially for Sichuan pickled vegetables,
# 后面写了一个怎么来
They published a recipe book
# 做这泡菜的一本菜谱
Only for Sichuan pickled vegetables
# 明白了 您这有数据
Right, you have the data (, so it is convincing).
# 那关于泡菜除了刚才的
About pickled vetetables,
# 还有其它推荐吃法吗
Do you have any other recommendations?
# 推荐吃法多
Sure
# 刚才说烧鱼
It goes well with braising fish
# 汆丸子 酸菜鱼
Meat ball soup, fish soup
# 我吃点米饭
Even with plain rice
# 用这泡菜剁碎了
Chop the pickled vegetables in small pieces
# 用点肉粒一炒
Stir fry with some meat
# 那香极了
Would smell amazing too.
# 朝鲜泡菜和韩国泡菜
Also, the kimchi from Korea
# 在中国
Is also popular in China
# 大家为什么有时候喜欢
What we love to do
# 夏天我们来一碗凉面
Is making a cold noodle in the hot summer
# 就用他们那个泡菜汤
With kimchi soup
# 配着他们这泡菜
And the kimchi on top
# 那要吃一碗凉面 那很爽
It’s perfect for summer days, isn’t it?
# 我们中餐也可以
Chinese food can go well
# 我们配点韩国的泡菜
With Korean kimchi
# 搞一中西结合也好吃
It’s a good combination.
# 上次安大厨
Last time we had Chef An here
# 给我们做的泡菜汤
Who made a perfect kimchi soup for us
# 非常的爽口
Very refreshing.
# 他们那个大的苏子叶
They use the perilla leaves
# 卷上泡菜再卷上肉
To make a roll with kimchi and roasted meat
# 这不中国跟韩国结合了吗
What a combination!
# 这才好吃呢
It tastes amazing.
# 好嘞 谢谢 太牛了
OK, thank you very much. That’s great!